Hi everyone.
مرحبًا بكم
I'm an artist and a dad -- second time around.
أنا فنان، وأب للمرة الثانية على التوالي.
Thank you.
شكرًا
And I want to share with you my latest art project.
وأريد أن أشارككم آخر مشاريعي الفنية
It's a children's book for the iPad.
إنه كتاب أطفال لجهاز iPad
It's a little quirky and silly.
وهو مميز وبسيط نوعًا ما
It's called "Pop-It,"
عنوانه "Pop-it"
And it's about the things little kids do with their parents.
ويتعلق بالأشياء التي يفعلها الأطفال مع آبائهم
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So this is about potty training --
فهذا يتعلق بالتدريب على القعادة --
as most of you, I hope, know.
الذي يعرفه معظمكم كما آمل
You can tickle the rug.
يمكنكم تحريك البساط
You can make the baby poop.
أو جعل الطفل يقضي حاجته
You can do all those fun things.
يمكنكم القيام بكل هذه الأشياء المسلية..
You can burst bubbles.
تفجير الفقاعات
You can draw, as everyone should.
الرسم، كما يجب على الجميع
But you know, I have a problem with children's books:
لكني لدي مشكلة مع كتب الأطفال:
I think they're full of propaganda.
أظنها مليئة بالدعاية
At least an Indian trying to get one of these American books in Park Slope, forget it.
على الأقل هندي يحاول الحصول على كتاب أمريكي في بارك سلوب، انسوا الأمر.
It's not the way I was brought up.
ليس ذلك ما نشأت عليه..
So I said, "I'm going to counter this with my own propaganda."
فقررت أن أواجه ذلك بدعايتي الخاصة
If you notice carefully,
إن لاحظتم جيدًا،
it's a homosexual couple bringing up a child.
تجدوا زوجين مثليين يربيان طفلًا
You don't like it?
ألا يعجبكم ذلك؟
Shake it, and you have a lesbian couple.
حركوها، ليصبح لديكم سحاقيتان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Shake it, and you have a heterosexual couple.
حركوها، ولديكم زوجان عاديان
You know, I don't even believe in the concept of an ideal family.
أتعرفون، لا أؤمن بمبدأ الأسرة المثالية
I have to tell you about my childhood.
سأخبركم بطفولتي..
I went to this very proper Christian school
ذهبت إلى مدرسة مسيحية محافظة
taught by nuns, fathers, brothers, sisters.
درس لي الراهبات والآباء والإخوة والأخوات..
Basically, I was brought up to be a good Samaritan,
وتربيت في الأساس لأصبح سامريًا صالحًا
and I am.
وأنا كذلك.
And I'd go at the end of the day to a traditional Hindu house,
وكنت أذهب في نهاية اليوم إلى منزل هندوسي تقليدي،
which was probably the only Hindu house
والذي كان ربما البيت الهندوسي الوحيد
in a predominantly Islamic neighborhood.
في حي أغلب سكانه من المسلمين
Basically, I celebrated every religious function.
احتفلت بكل مناسبة دينية
In fact, when there was a wedding in our neighborhood,
فحين يكون هناك عرس في الحي،
all of us would paint our houses for the wedding.
كنا نطلي منازلنا من أجل العرس..
I remember we cried profusely
أتذكر أننا بكينا بشدة
when the little goats we played with in the summer
حين تحول الماعز الذي لعبنا معه في الصيف
became biriani.
إلى برياني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We all had to fast during Ramadan.
كان علينا جميعا أن نصوم رمضان
It was a very beautiful time.
كان زمنًا جميلًا
But I must say,
لكن علي أن أقول
I'll never forget, when I was 13 years old, this happened.
لن أنسى أبدًا ما حدث في ال13 من عمري
Babri Masjid --
مسجد بابري --
one of the most beautiful mosques in India,
أحد أجمل مساجد الهند،
built by King Babur, I think, in the 16th century --
بناه الملك بابور في القرن ال16 كما أظن --
was demolished by Hindu activists.
هدمه نشطاء هندوس.
This caused major riots in my city.
مما أدى إلى أعمال شغب كبيرة في مدينتي
And for the first time,
وللمرة الأولى
I was affected
كنت متضررًا..
by this communal unrest.
من الاضطرابات الطائفية
My little five-year-old kid neighbor
جاري ذو الخمس سنوات
comes running in,
جاءني يجري
and he says, "Rags, Rags.
قائلًا "راجز، راجز
You know the Hindus are killing us Muslims. Be careful."
الهندوس يقتلوننا نحن المسلمين، فاحذر."
I'm like, "Dude, I'm Hindu."
فأجبته "أنا هندوسي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He's like, "Huh!"
فأجابني "هه!"
You know, my work is inspired
أستلهم عملي..
by events such as this.
من أحداث كهذه،
Even in my gallery shows,
وحتى في معرض صوري،
I try and revisit historic events
أحاول أن أعيد زيارة أحداث تاريخية
like Babri Masjid,
كمسجد بابري،
distill only its emotional residue
واستخلاص بقاياها العاطفية فقط
and image my own life.
وتخيل حياتي الخاصة.
Imagine history being taught differently.
تخيل أن يتم تدريس التاريخ بشكل مختلف
Remember that children's book
أتذكرون كتاب الأطفال..
where you shake and the sexuality of the parents change?
حيث تحركونه فيتغير جنس الوالدين؟
I have another idea.
لدي فكرة أخرى..
It's a children's book about Indian independence --
كتاب أطفال حول استقلال الهند --
very patriotic.
شديد الوطنية
But when you shake it, you get Pakistan's perspective.
لكن حين تحركوه تجدوا وجهة النظر الباكستانية
Shake it again, and you get the British perspective.
وتحركوه مجددًا، فتحصلوا على وجهة النظر البريطانية
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You have to separate fact from bias, right.
عليك الفصل بين الحقائق والنزعات، صحيح
Even my books on children
حتى كتبي للأطفال
have cute, fuzzy animals.
فيها حيوانات غامضة ولطيفة..
But they're playing geopolitics.
لكنها ترمز إلى السياسية الطبيعية
They're playing out Israel-Palestine,
فتقوم بدور فلسطين وإسرائيل،
India-Pakistan.
الهند وباكستان
You know, I'm making a very important argument.
تعرفون، أنني أحاول الوصول إلى برهان مهم
And my argument [is]
ألا وهو..
that the only way for us to teach creativity
أن الطريقة الوحيدة لتعليم الإبداع
is by teaching children perspectives
هو تعليم الأطفال وجهات النظر
at the earliest stage.
في المرحلة المبكرة.
After all, children's books are manuals on parenting,
ففي الغالب كتب الأطفال هي كتيبات عن تربية الأطفال،
so you better give them children's books that teach them perspectives.
لذا يفضل إعطاؤهم كتب أطفال تعلمهم وجهات نظر.
And conversely,
وبالمقابل..
only when you teach perspectives
فقط حين تُعلم وجهات النظر
will a child be able to imagine
يمكن للطفل أن يتخيل
and put themselves in the shoes
ويضع نفسه مكان..
of someone who is different from them.
شخص آخر مختلف عنه تمامًا،
I'm making an argument that art and creativity
أحاول أن أبرهن على أن الفن والإبداع
are very essential tools in empathy.
أداتان أساسيتان لفهم الآخر
You know, I can't promise my child
لا أستطيع أن أعد طفلي
a life without bias --
بحياة دون انحياز-
we're all biased --
كلنا ننحاز-
but I promise to bias my child with multiple perspectives.
لكني أعد بأن أجعله ينحاز إلى تعدد وجهات النظر
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)